Guide to the Isaac Mann Autograph Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Isaac Mann autograph collection
1750-1831
OSB MSS 46
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of 86 documents, mostly letters, gathered by Mann for their signatures. Most of the individuals represented are clergymen or preachers, particularly Baptists, and include Abraham Booth, Christmas Evans, Samuel Kilpin, John Ryland, and Basil Woodd.
Mann, Isaac, 1785-1831
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
ISAAC MANN, 1785-1831 (COLLECTOR)
Isaac Mann, was born in 1785 and joined the Particular (Reformed) Baptist Church at Bridlington in Yorkshire during the ministry of Robert Harness of Hull. He was the first student admitted to the new Horton Academy in April, 1805. After brief pastorates at Steep Lane, Burslem, and Shipley Baptist churches, Mann returned to Horton as tutor in Classics in 1816. He was named Secretary to the Northern (Baptist) Education Society in 1822, and became pastor at Maze Pond Chapel in London in 1826. Mann died in London in 1831.
Scope and Contents
The Isaac Mann Autograph Collection consists of letters and documents by religious figures, especially Baptist or Particular Baptist ministers, collected by Isaac Mann, himself a Particular Baptist minister. The collection spans the dates 1750-1849 and the items have been arranged alphabetically by author.
With the exception of a few notes to Mann concerning his search for autograph material, there are no letters to Mann himself in the collection. It does contain letters to and by several influential Baptist missionaries and their supporters, including David Brown, William Bull, William Carey, Christmas Evans, Andrew Fuller, and Samuel Pearce. An 1807 letter by Carey, for example, discusses the sale in England of his Sanskrit grammar and translation of the Ramayana. A number of letters are requests for assistance from or comments on the work of the Particular Baptist Fund. One such letter, addressed by Benjamin Tomkins on behalf of the Fund to the Rev. Thomas Linford of Bottsford, requests a "sincere, but also satisfactory" answer to the the Fund's concerns about Linford's teachings on the Moral Law.
There are several letters by Abraham Booth, pastor of Little Prescot-Street church in London, including defenses of his Glad Tidings to Perishing Sinners, or, the Genuine Gospel a Complete Warrant for the Ungodly to Believe in Jesus and a comment that American "metaphysical theology" may "issue in doctrinal Arminianism, and practical Antinomianism."
John Ryland (1753-1825), pastor of Broadmead, Bristol, is represented by eight items, including a 1796 letter commenting on Robertson's Historical Disquisition, notes on some scripture verses, and a short text in question and answer format on John 6:37 titled "Come and Welcome to Jesus Christ."
One of the few items by a non-Baptist is the earliest item in the collection, a sermon fragment in the hand of the Nonconforming minister Philip Henry (1631-1696). Another is a March 13, 1849 letter by the Rev. James Shore of the Free Church of England, written during his imprisonment at Exeter Gaol for preaching without a license. Addressed to the Rev. John Blackburn, the letter states that Shore is "very happy in his cell" and expresses his hope for the "entire liberation of religion from secular influence."
Other material includes an undated sermon fragment in the hand of \ Philip Henry (1631-1696); the deathbed letter of the Rev. Joseph Stennett to his parishioners; a letter by the Rev. Alexander Waugh discussing his own early religious exercises; and an incomplete notebook of "Poems on Several Occasions" and "Juvenilia," with notes on metrics, by Thomas Gibbons.
Clergy -- England -- Autographs; Autographs (manuscripts); Clergy; Binney, Thomas, 1798-1874 -- Autograph; Booth, Abraham, 1734-1806 -- Autograph; Evans, Christmas, 1766-1838 -- Autograph; Gibbons, Thomas, 1720-1785 -- Autograph; Kilpin, S(Samuel), 1774-1830 -- Autograph; Mann, Isaac, 1785-1831; Pearce, Samuel, 1766-1799 -- Autograph; Raffles, Thomas, 1788-1863 -- Autograph; Ryland, John, 1753-1825 -- Autograph; Stennett, Samuel, 1727-1795 -- Autograph; Woodd, Basil, 1760-1831 -- Autograph
- Letters and Documents, DATES: 1751-1849; Series I; 0.21' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Letters and Documents is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - BINNEY, THOMAS, 1798-1874
    - ALS to Isaac Mann; [n.p.], [1831] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS to unnamed recipient; [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Gives corrections on text of recipient's address.
  - BOOTH, ABRAHAM, 1734-1806
    - ALS to Robert Harness; London, 1804 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Concerns the possibility of Harness's taking the Baptist church in Broseley, Shropshire.
    - ALS to John Webster Morris; London, 1798 Jun 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Returns a MS of Samuel Hopkins and defends himself against its arguments.
    - ALS to Mr. Pudner; Fieldgate, [1774] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Concerns the possible publication of Mr. Rowles's answer to a tract by Joshua Toulmin.
    - ALS to John Ryland; London, 1798 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Defends himself against misrepresentations in a MS on justification by Dr. Hopkins and criticizes metaphysical theology of American authors which might lead to Arminianism.
    - ALS to Betsey and Mary Wightman; London, 1803 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Sends a parcel of their grandmother's clothes and advises on their deportment.
    - Receipt, signed, 1796 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Receipt for L110.10.5 to Particular Baptist Fund.
  - BROADFOOT, WILLIAM
    - ALS to Mr. Paxon, [n.y.] Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Encloses some addresses.
  - BROWN, DAVID, 1763-1812
    - Letter (copy) to Joshua Marshman, [1803 or later] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Asks about progress of translations of Bible into languages of India.
  - BULL, THOMAS PALMER, 1773-1859
    - ALS to John Clayton; Newport, 1829 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Reports that he is unable to admit a recommended student to Newport Pagnell Academy.
  - BULL, WILLIAM, 1738-1814
    - ALS to John Sutcliff, 1794 Nov 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      About William Carey's missionary efforts.
  - CAREY, WILLIAM, 1761-1854
    - Petition to the Managers of the Particular Baptist Fund; Moulton, 1786 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Holograph. Acknowledges receipt of gift and solicits further aid.
    - Petition to the Managers of the Particular Baptist Fund; Moulton, 1786 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Holograph. Petitions for an allowance "for the Purchase of Books necessary for a Minister." With signed recommendation by John Evans and John Ryland.
    - Two petitions to the Managers of the Particular Baptist Fund; Leicester, 1790 Oct 30-31 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Holograph. Acknowledges receipt of a donation and solicits further aid. Also signed by Deacons and members of the Baptist Church in Leicester.
    - ALS to unnamed recipient; Calcutta, 1807 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Gives instructions for selling the first volume of his Ramayana and Sanskrit grammer, and relates plans for translations of the Bible.
  - COLLYER, WILLIAM BENGO, 1782-1854
    - ALS to Joseph Maitland; Peckham, 1828 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Concerns votes by proxy.
  - ERSKINE, JOHN, 1721?-1803
    - 2 ALS to John Ryland; Lauriston, 1801, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Sends pamphlets (not present) about American theology.
    - ALS to John Sutcliff; Lauriston, 1799 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - EVANS, CHRISTMAS, 1766-1838
    - ALS to William Paxson; Cardiff, 1829 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Reviews his ministry in the last year, his gifts from the Baptist Fund, and his state of health. Followed by an ALS to the Managers of the Particular Baptist Fund, dated 1829 Jan 4, giving a short summary of his faith and soliciting further aid.
    - Document, signed, recommending David Thomas, [1814 or later] (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Holograph. Also signed by Joseph Harris and Timothy Thomas. Supports effort to gather books to aid ministry in Gower, Glamorganshire.
    - ALS to unidentified recipient; Llangefni, 1813 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      About efforts to get signatures for a petition to Parliament for the protection of the Baptist Mission in India.
  - FULLER, ANDREW, 1754-1815
    - ALS to J. Edwards; Kettering, 1814 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Concerns collections for the Baptist Missionary Society and giving news about William Carey's effort in India.
    - ALS to John Sutcliff; Kettering, 1808 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      With references to several Baptists and translations of the Bible.
    - Memorandum, [1814] (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Holograph. Concerning the Baptist Missionary Society. Accompanied by partial minutes of a meeting of the Baptist Missionary Society.
  - GIBBONS, THOMAS, 1720-1785
    - ALS to Mr. Baker; Bunhill Row, [1750] Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Letter to a man facing death.
    - [Poems on several occasions], [ca. 1744-50] (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Holograph. Concerning original verses and comments on poetry. Incomplete, lacking leaves of beginning.
  - HALL, ROBERT, 1764-1831
    - ALS to John Webster Morris; [n.p.], 1808 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Explains why he has abandoned plans for his publication.
  - HENRY, PHILIP, 1631-1696
    - Sermon notes, [17th cent.] (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Holograph fragment.
  - HUNTINGTON, EBENEZER, D. 1821
    - Memorandum (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Holograph. Endorsed by Isaac Mann.
  - KILPIN, SAMUEL, FL. 1820
    - 2 ALS to John Cocks, [ca. 1815] (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Urges him to preach to a man about to be executed and discusses the cost of building chapels.
    - 4 ALS to William Paxson, 1817-20 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Enquires about magazine proofs and mourns the death of a mutual friend.
  - MARSHMAN, JOSHUA, 1768-1837
    - ALS to Joseph Ivimey, 1827 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - MORISON, JOHN, 1791-1859
    - ALS to Rev. Thomas Thomas; Hans Place, 1833 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Declines an invitation to preach.
    - ALS to John Paxson; Hans Place, 1836 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Declines an unstated request.
  - NOEL, BAPTIST WRIOTHESLEY, 1798-1873
    - 2 ALS to unnamed recipients, 1841, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Responds to requests to preach.
  - ORME, WILLIAM, 1787-1830
    - ALS to Isaac Mann; Grove Lane, 1826 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Sends two or three autographs, now missing, of men "who will probably be remembered when the hand which now writes this will be mouldering in the dust."
  - OWEN, JOHN 1766-1822
    - ALS to the Rev. John Clayton, 1816 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Asks him to second the resolution of thanks to the Vice President at an upcoming meeting, possibly the British and Foreign Bible Society.
    - AL (3d person) to Messrs. Cadell and Davies; Fulham, [1796] Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Requests 25 copies of his Travels to be sent to John Bacon, Esq.
  - PEARCE, SAMUEL, 1766-1799
    - ALS to Andrew Fuller; Tamerton, 1799 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Sends recommendations for advice to be sent by Baptist Missionary Society to their missionaries. Printed in Fuller's Memoirs ... of Samuel Pearce.
    - ALS to William Steadman; Birmingham, 1795 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Reports the news he has received from William Carey in India on the Baptist Missions.
  - PIKE, JOHN DEODATUS GREGORY, 1784-1854
    - ALS to unnamed recipient; Derby, 1827 Feb 22 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Concerns the printing of an edition of his Persuasives to early piety being executed by Richard Baynes.
  - RAFFLES, THOMAS, 1788-1863
    - 2 ALS to Isaac Mann; Liverpool, 1820, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Sends the autograph (still present) of Thomas Spencer, "the fifth edition of whose life goes to press ... on Monday," and comments on Mann's autograph collection.
    - ALS to Rev. G. B. Kidd; Liverpool, 1821 Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Expresses willingness to conduct service.
    - ALS to Rev. Moses Fisher, [1824] (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Invitation to dine.
  - REED, ANDREW, 1787-1862.
    - ALS to Isaac Mann, 1826 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Arranges a time for Mann to preach.
  - RIPPON, JOHN 1751-1836
    - 2 ALS to Mr. B. Lepard, 1817, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Concerns the need of a grant from the Particular Baptist Fund for the chapel at Uppenham.
  - ROBINSON, THOMAS, 1749-1813
    - ALS to John Ryland; Leicester, 1790 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      With notes, possibly for a sermon, by Ryland.
  - RYLAND, JOHN, 1753-1825
    - ALS to unnamed recipient, 1796 Jun 25 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      With comments on Robertson's Historical Disquisitions ... 1791, and accompanied by sermon notes on various scripture passages, 1783 or ca. 1800.
    - ALS to Joseph Tyso, [1809 or later] (Box 1, Folder 50)
      Concerns efforts to find another church for Mr. Tyso.
    - ALS to William Burls; [Bristol], 1813 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 51)
      Sends Bristol Petitions (now absent) to be placed before Parliament by Richard Davis and Edward Protheroe.
    - ALS to the Rev. Mr. Sutcliff, 1795 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Inquires into Sutcliff's activities, with comments on various Baptist divines and articles in the Evangelical Magazine.
    - ALS to John Webster Morris, [1804 May 30] (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Requests back issues of a periodical on Baptist missions and chronicles religious meetings.
    - ALS to the Rev. Mr. Wilcocks, [1821 Jan 19] (Box 1, Folder 54)
      About a collection for poor ministers, with the money to go to Mr. Cocks of Culstock.
    - ALS to [John Rippon], [1825 May 10] (Box 1, Folder 55)
      Gives his opinion of the case between the Barnstaple Baptist Church and Mr. John's.
    - AL to unnamed recipient, [ca. 1800] (Box 1, Folder 56)
      Letter commends the ministry of Mr. Bradley, Baptist divine. Also signed by John Sharp.
  - SHALER, THOMAS, FL. 1790
    - Petition to the Managers of the Particular Baptist Fund, signed on behalf of the church at Cardington, Bedford, Cardington, 1790 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      Solicits further aid and claims greater need on account of the death of John Howard, who had contributed to the church.
  - SHORE, JAMES
    - ALS to John Blackburn; Exeter, 1849 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      Writes from the Exeter Gaol, where he had been imprisoned for his actions in trying to effect the "liberation of religion from secular influence."
  - SIMPSON, DAVID, 1745-1799
    - Sermon notes, [ca. 1790] (Box 1, Folder 59)
      Holograph. Endorsed by Simpson's son, David Simpson, and by Isaac Mann.
  - SIMPSON, ROBERT, 1764-1817
    - ALS to John Hirst; Bolton, 1789 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      Responds to queries of Hirst about Baptist meetings in Bolton.
  - SMITH, JOHN PYE, 1774-1851
    - ALS to Thomas Blundell; London, 1827 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      Recommends Mr. Tomkins to the Committee of the Stepney Baptist Academy.
  - STEARNE, EDWARD, FL. 1827-1838
    - ALS to Samuel Davis; Camberwill, 1827 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Asks Davis if he will preach in Stearne's church the following Sunday.
    - ALS to W. Paxson; Fen Court, 1838 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      Letter of introduction.
  - STENNETT, JOSEPH, 1692-1758
    - LS to the Church of Christ meeting in Little Wild Street, London, Bath, 1757 Nov 30 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      Dictated and signed by Joseph Stennett, and written by Samuel Stennett. A farewell letter to his congregation before his death.
  - STENNETT, JOSEPH, FL. 1808
    - ALS to Mr. Clark, Bampton, 1808 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      Answers a query about the Baptist Church in Little Wild Street.
  - STENNETT, SAMUEL, 1728-1795
    - ALS to the Church of Christ meeting in Little Wild Street; Bartholomew Close, 1758 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 66)
      Accepts their call to be minister.
    - ALS to Gilbert Pudner; Muswell Hill, 1765 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - STENNETT, SAMUEL, 1780?-1841
    - ALS to the Rev. T. Griffin, 1829 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 68)
      Applies for support and inquires about a church in which to serve.
  - THOMAS, JOHN, 1757-1801
    - ALS to Andrew Fuller, 1796 Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 69)
      Reports to Baptist Missionary Society on his efforts in India.
    - ALS to James Smith, Leominster, 1789 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 70)
      Gives facts about the career of Joseph Stennett.
  - TOMKINS, BENJAMIN, FL. 1798
    - Letter (copy) to the Rev. Thomas Linford, 1798 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 71)
      Inquires on behalf of the Managers of the Particular Baptist Fund whether Linford believes moral law to be the rule of a Christian's moral conduct. Copy by Abraham Booth.
  - WAUGH, ALEXANDER, 1754-1827
    - ALS to the Rev. James Churchill, 1817 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 72)
      Regrets that he is unable to preach at Dillon and sends sympathy to Mr. Churchill during his distress.
    - ALS to John Ross, 1821 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 73)
      Recalls his religious experience as a child. Accompanied by copy in another hand.
  - WINSLOW, OCTAVIUS
    - ALS to William Paxon, 1831 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 74)
      Announces a sermon on the American revival.
  - WOODD, BASIL, 1760-1831
    - ALS to Joseph Ivimey; Paddington, 1813 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 75)
      Discusses possibility of interdenominational approach to missionary work.